A Finding Aid to the Kenneth and Emma-Stina Prescott Research Material on Artists, 1919-2001, bulk 1973-1991, in the Archives of American Art AAA.preskenn
Archives of American Art
Kenneth and Emma-Stina Prescott research material on artists
bulk 1973-1991
1919-2001
AAA.preskenn
Archives of American Art
9.4 Linear feet
The Kenneth and Emma-Stina Prescott research material on artists measures 9.4 linear feet and dates from 1919 to 2001, with the bulk of the material dating from 1973 to 1991. Kenneth Prescott, an art historian and educator, and his wife Emma-Stina, also an art historian, maintained extensive files concerning artists James Chapin, Burgoyne Diller, Dorothea S. Greenbaum, Jack Levine, and Elizabeth Olds. These files typically include correspondence, artwork inventories, exhibition catalogs and other printed materials, notes, interviews, photographs, and slides. A small amount of material also documents the works of Richard Anuszkiewicz, Byron Browne, Jose de Creeft, Lorrie Goulet, Richard Hunt, Sam Maitin, and Hunt Slonem.
Prescott, Emma-Stina
Prescott, Kenneth Wade, 1920-
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
The collection was donated in several installments by Kenneth and Emma-Stina Prescott from 1987 to 2001.
Arrangement note
The collection is arranged as 6 series.
Series 1: James Chapin, 1941, 1955-circa 1984 (0.5 linear feet; Box 1)
Series 2: Burgoyne Diller, 1932-2001 (2.5 linear feet; Boxes 1-3)
Series 3: Dorothea S. Greenbaum, 1919-1980 (2.7 linear feet; Boxes 4-6)
Series 4: Jack Levine, 1961-1991 (2.1 linear feet; Boxes 6-8)
Series 5: Elizabeth Olds, 1931-1992 (0.6 linear feet; Boxes 8-9)
Series 6: Other Artists, 1929-1998 (1.0 linear foot; Boxes 9-10)
Conditions Governing Access note
Use of original papers requires an appointment. Use of archival audiovisual recordings with no duplicate access copy requires advance notice.
Biographical/Historical note
Kenneth Wade Prescott (1920-2013) was an art historian and educator in Austin, Texas. Prescott’s wife, Emma-Stina is also an art historian.
Kenneth Prescott received a Ph.D. in Zoology from the University of Michigan. While living in Ann Arbor he met his future wife Emma-Stina Johnsson, who was visiting from Stockholm, Sweden. His early career included directorships of the Kansas City Museum, Academy of Natural Sciences in Philadelphia, and the New Jersey State Museum. During his career he arranged and curated many exhibitions throughout the country and abroad and administered a grant program in the visual arts for the Ford Foundation. He and his wife moved to Austin, Texas in 1974, and he served as Chairman of the Art Department at the University of Texas at Austin. While there he introduced a Ph.D. program in Art History. Prescott regularly published in the fields of ornithology and the visual arts, including several publications on Ben Shahn and retrospective exhibition catalogs for the works of Elizabeth Olds, Burgoyne Diller, and Jack Levine. He also collaborated with his wife on The Complete Graphic Work of Jack Levine which was published in 1984.
Related Archival Materials note
Also found at the Archives of American Art are the Burgoyne Diller papers which include papers and artwork donated by Kenneth and Emma-Stina Prescott. The Kenneth W. Prescott and Emma-Stina Prescott Collection of Ben Shahn is available at the Harry Ransom Humanities Research Center, University of Texas at Austin.
Scope and Contents note
The Kenneth and Emma-Stina Prescott research material on artists measures 9.4 linear feet and dates from 1919 to 2001, with the bulk of the material dating from 1973 to 1991. Kenneth Prescott, an art historian and educator, and his wife Emma-Stina, also an art historian, maintained extensive files concerning artists James Chapin, Burgoyne Diller, Dorothea S. Greenbaum, Jack Levine, and Elizabeth Olds. These files typically include correspondence, artwork inventories, exhibition catalogs and other printed materials, notes, interviews, photographs, and slides. A small amount of material also documents the works of Richard Anuszkiewicz, Byron Browne, Jose de Creeft, Lorrie Goulet, Richard Hunt, Sam Maitin, and Hunt Slonem.
Anuszkiewicz, Richard; Browne, Byron, 1907-1961; Chapin, James, 1887-1975; De Creeft, José, 1884-; Diller, Burgoyne, 1906-1965; Goulet, Lorrie, 1925-; Greenbaum, Dorothea S.; Hunt, Richard, 1935-; Levine, Jack; Maitin, Sam; Olds, Elizabeth, 1896-1991; Slonem, Hunt; Art historians; Artists--United States; Interviews; Photographs
- James Chapin, 1955-circa 1984; 1941; Series 1; 0.5 Linear feet Box 1
  Scope and Contents note
  James Chapin research material primarily consists of correspondence, printed material, photographs, and artwork inventories. Prescott’s correspondence is with the Chapin family, museums, galleries, collectors, publishers, and others regarding an exhibition and catalog of Chapin’s work at the Yaneff Gallery, Toronto. Also found are originals and photocopies of printed material documenting exhibitions of Chapin’s work, and photocopies of inventory cards which include sales information. Photographic materials depict artwork by Chapin, and other miscellaneous research material includes printed material, lists, and photocopies of biographical data.
  Arrangement note
  Printed materials were removed from binders into archival folders. These documents are photocopies annotated by Prescott during the 1970s, but are arranged in chronological order by original publication date, which is provided in parentheses.
  - Correspondence, 1973-1979 (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
  - Inventory and Sales, circa 1984 (Box 1, Folder 3-5)
  - Printed Materials (1924-1978), 1970s (Box 1, Folder 6-9)
  - Time Covers, 1955-1960 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Photographs, 1968; 1970s (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Color Transparencies and Negatives, circa 1970s (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Miscellaneous Research Material, circa 1974-1980; 1941 (Box 1, Folder 13-14)
- Burgoyne Diller, 1932-2001; Series 2; 2.5 Linear feet Boxes 1-3
  Found here is extensive research material regarding Burgoyne Diller. Included are photocopies of the Diller Estate’s inventory records, notecards containing artwork inventory information, photographs and slides of Diller’s artwork, exhibition catalogs, and a thesis about Diller. Also found are records which Kenneth Prescott categorized as “Diller Archival,” consisting of photocopies of Diller’s own archive of correspondence, biographical information, and writings. Additional printed material includes annotated photocopies of news clippings and exhibition publications regarding Diller’s career. Other photographs depict Diller and installations of two retrospective exhibitions of his work.
  Much of the research material was removed from binders and placed into archival folders. The original order of the documents has been maintained. Photocopies were annotated by Prescott and date from the 1970s but are arranged in chronological order by original publication date, which is provided in parentheses.
  - Diller Archival - Correspondence/Records/etc., circa 1970s (Box 1, Folder 15-26)
  - Estate Inventory Records, circa 1970s (Box 1, Folder 27-31)
  - Diller Archival - His Writings, circa 1970s (Box 1, Folder 32-37)
  - Poem by Diller, undated (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Catalogue/Exhibition Data (1932-1991), 1970s-1991 (Box 2, Folder 1-6)
  - Thesis, "Burgoyne Diller: A Neo-Plasticist" by Anita J. Ellis, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Printed Material (1920s-1991), 1970s-1991 (Box 2, Folder 8-14)
  - Magazines, 1968; 1961 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Exhibition Catalogs, 1932-1995 (Box 2, Folder 16-30)
  - Photographs of Diller, circa 1935-1960s (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Photographs of Exhibition Installations, 1987; 1981 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Photographs of Artwork, circa 1970s (Box 3, Folder 3-5)
  - Color Transparencies of Artwork, circa 1970s (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Negatives, circa 1970s (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Slide Inventory, 2001 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Slides, circa 1960s-1980s (Box 3, Folder 9-17)
  - Notecards, circa 1970s (Box 3, Folder 18)
- Dorothea S. Greenbaum, 1919-1980; Series 3; 2.7 Linear feet Boxes 4-6
  Research material on Dorothea S. Greenbaum primarily consists of documentation for a catalogue raisonne that was never published. Included is Prescott’s correspondence with Greenbaum, artists, collectors, galleries, dealers, curators, publishers, and others. Also found are an artwork inventory; notecards documenting titles of works, dates, and owners; “problems” regarding specific works of art; and several draft versions of the catalogue raisonne. Also of note are a draft autobiography written by Greenbaum and a transcript of an interview of Greenbaum by Prescott. Printed material includes photocopies and originals of news clippings, exhibition catalogs, press releases, and invitations. Additional photographs depict Greenbaum at gallery events and in her studio. Included is one photograph of Yasuo Kuniyoshi standing next to a Greenbaum sculpture.
  Much of this material was removed from binders and placed into archival folders. The original order of the documents has been maintained.
  - Correspondence, 1970-1980 (Box 4, Folder 1-4)
  - Interview Transcript, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Inventory, 1970s (Box 4, Folder 6-8)
  - Problems, circa 1973-1978 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Notecards, circa 1970s (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Catalogue Raisonne Drafts, circa 1970s (Box 5, Folder 1-7)
  - Essay and Notes, circa 1970s (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Autobiography, 1973-1977 (Box 5, Folder 9-10)
  - Printed Materials, 1928-1979 (Box 5, Folder 11-16)
  - Exhibition Catalogs, 1933-1941 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Exhibition Catalogs, 1952-1977 (Box 6, Folder 1-3)
  - Drawings, undated (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Photographs of Dorothea S. Greenbaum and Others, circa 1933-1975 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Photographs of Sculptures, circa 1926-1975 (Box 6, Folder 6-15)
  - Photographs of Artwork, 1920s-1970s (Box 6, Folder 16-17)
  - Negatives, circa 1970s (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - Miscellaneous Research Material, 1919; 1939-1979 (Box 6, Folder 19-20)
- Jack Levine, 1961-1991; Series 4; 2.1 Linear feet Boxes 6-8
  Found here is research material on Jack Levine, primarily compiled for a traveling Levine retrospective (1979-1980) and The Complete Graphic Works of Jack Levine (1984), written by Kenneth and Emma-Stina Prescott. Included are notecards with artwork inventory details, inventory worksheets, Prescott’s correspondence regarding the availability of Levine’s work for the planned retrospective, and many slides and photographs of artwork. Also found are writings on Levine by Henry Arnold Freedman and transcripts of two interviews of Levine by Kenneth Prescott. Additional photographs include two portraits of Levine and photographs of Levine and the Prescotts at the opening of the retrospective exhibition. General research material primarily consists of photocopies of news clippings, exhibition publications, letters, and biographical material about Levine.
  General research materials were removed from binders into archival folders. These documents are mostly photocopies annotated by Prescott during the 1970s, but are arranged in chronological order by original publication date, which is provided in parentheses.
  - Correspondence, 1977-1980 (Box 6, Folder 21-27)
  - Exhibition Catalogs, 1961-1986 (Box 6, Folder 28-29)
  - Publication, The Complete Graphic Works of Jack Levine, 1984 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Thesis, "The WPA Paintings of Jack Levine" by Henry Arnold Freedman, 1967 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Dissertation, "Jack Levine: Painter and Protester" by Henry Arnold Freedman, 1974 (Box 7, Folder 3-4)
  - Transcript of Interview with Jack Levine by Kenneth Prescott, 1970s (Box 7, Folder 5-8)
  - Transcript of Interview with Jack Levine by Kenneth Prescott, 1978 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Inventory Worksheets, 1970s (Box 7, Folder 10-15)
  - Notecards, circa 1970s (Box 7, Folder 16-17)
  - Research Material for Jack Levine Retrospective Exhibition Catalog, circa 1978 (Box 7, Folder 18-19)
  - Research Material, General (1936-1949), 1970s (Box 7, Folder 20-23)
  - Research Material, General (1950-1991), 1970s-1991 (Box 8, Folder 1-18)
  - Photographs of Jack Levine, 1963; 1970 (Box 8, Folder 19)
  - Photographs of Jack Levine Retrospective, 1978 (Box 8, Folder 20)
  - Photographs of Artwork, 1970s (Box 8, Folder 21-25)
  - Slides, 1970s (Box 8, Folder 26-27)
- Elizabeth Olds, 1931-1992; Series 5; 0.6 Linear feet Boxes 8-9
  Found here is research material regarding artist Elizabeth Olds, including exhibition catalogs and other printed material, photographs and slides of her artwork, an appraisal of her artwork, and a thesis on her career. Also found are a few snapshots of Olds, primarily depicting her sketching outdoors. Recordings include one audio cassette of Olds interviewed by Kenneth Prescott and one videocassette of Olds interviewed at age 88 and a selection of works shown in her 1986 retrospective exhibition at the RGK Foundation.
  - Personal Property Appraisal, 1992 (Box 8, Folder 28)
  - Thesis, "Elizabeth Olds: Graphic Artist of the 1930s" by Susan Ellizabeth Arthur, 1985 (Box 8, Folder 29)
  - Exhibition Catalogs, 1931-1992 (Box 8, Folder 30)
  - Printed Material, 1980s (Box 8, Folder 31)
  - Photographs of Elizabeth Olds, 1985; undated (Box 8, Folder 32)
  - Photographs of Artwork, circa 1965-1985 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Slides, 1980s (Box 9, Folder 2-3)
  - Interview of Elizabeth Olds, 1983 May 5; 1 Sound cassettes (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Elizabeth Olds Interview and Artworks, circa 1986; 1 Videocassettes (VHS) (Box 9, Folder 5)
- Other Artists, 1929-1998; Series 6; 1 Linear feet Boxes 9-10
  Found here is a small amount of research material on other artists including Richard Anuszkiewicz, Jose de Creeft, Byron Browne, Lorrie Goulet, Richard Hunt, Hunt Slonem, and Sam Maitin. Documentation primarily includes slides of artwork and exhibition catalogs, but may also include other biographical and printed material. Also found are artist-made Christmas cards and other artwork from various artists sent to the Prescotts.
  - Richard Anuszkiewicz, Resume, 1990 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Richard Anuszkiewicz, Exhibition Catalogs, 1965-1994 (Box 9, Folder 7-10)
  - Richard Anuszkiewicz, Clippings, 1963-1991 (Box 9, Folder 11-12)
  - Byron Browne, Slides, 1989 (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - Jose de Creeft, Exhibition Catalogs, 1929-1992 (Box 9, Folder 14-16)
  - Jose de Creeft, Printed Material, circa 1983-1986 (Box 9, Folder 17)
  - Jose de Creeft, Slides, circa 1980s (Box 9, Folder 18)
  - Lorrie Goulet, Exhibition Catalogs, 1971-1991 (Box 9, Folder 19)
  - Richard Hunt, Miscellaneous Research Material, 1960-1982 (Box 9, Folder 20-23)
  - Richard Hunt, Exhibition Catalogs, 1971-1976 (Box 9, Folder 24)
  - Richard Hunt, Exhibition Catalogs, 1976-1980 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Sam Maitin, Miscellaneous Research Material, 1971 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Maxwell Stewart Simpson, Christmas cards, 1966-1970 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Hunt Slonem, Exhibition Catalogs, 1983-1992 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Hunt Slonem, Slides, circa 1980s (Box 10, Folder 5-6)
  - Artwork by Other Artists, circa 1965-1998 (Box 10, Folder 7-8)
    Includes artwork by Ronald Mallory, Fletcher Benton, Larry Rivers, Roy Lichtenstein, Gregorio Prestopino, Elaine Breiger, Claire Van Vliet, Bernard Childs, Judith Grenell, Carla Binder, Margaret Putnam, Riva Helfond, and Bernece Hunter.